你可以去通知皇家学会的秘书
You may inform the Secretary of the Royal Society
我讲座的题目是
that I have entitled my lecture
"达尔文的根本性错误"
Darwin's Fundamental Error.
这会引发不少抗议的 先生
That'll raise a few hackles, sir.
可不是嘛
Will it not?
我得走了
I must be off.
这些人都要通知到
You can acknowledge all of these.
这家伙不错
There's a good chap.
谢谢
Thanks.
父亲
Father?
亲爱的 什么事
My dear?
昨晚你听到Roy的叫声了么
Did you hear how Roy barked last night?
太可怕了
It was dreadful.
不 我没有听见
No, no I didn't.
你听见了么 Bennett
Did you hear him Bennett?
我也没有 先生
I can't say I did, sir.
它不停地叫
He kept on and on.
还在咆哮
He howled too.
肯定是有人进了花园
I'm sure someone got into the garden.
有人闯入?
An intruder?
是的 因为
Well yes, because.
哦 父亲
Oh father
有人从窗户外
someone looked in at me,
看着我
at my window.
不可能
Impossible.
你是在做梦吧
You must have been dreaming.
Edith 没人能爬到你的窗口
Oh, Edith nobody could reach your window.
窗户离地面太远了
It's far too far off the ground.
我肯定不是在做梦
I'm sure I wasn't dreaming.
Bennett 你来负责
Bennett, you take charge
不然我就赶不上参加教工会议了
or I shall be late for the faculty meeting.
我让你的未婚夫来照顾你 亲爱的
I leave you in your fiance's care my dear.
如果他做你的丈夫
If he proves as good a husband to you as
也能像做我的助理那么出色
he has amanuenses to me,
你就是个幸运的女人
you'll be a fortunate woman.
缓和一下她的恐惧情绪 Bennett 我知道你能做到
Allay her fears Bennett. I know you can.
你相信我么
Can you believe me?
没法轻易相信啊
Not easily, no.
就像你父亲说的
I mean as your father said.
那你就来看看
Come and look.
我实在是太忙了 这些关于松鼠猴的笔记要打印
I'm awfully busy with these notes on Saimiri Sciureus to type,
然后是你父亲关于论证...
and then the proof of your father's...
Jack 我不是在做梦
Jack, I know I wasn't dreaming
你知道Roy不会无缘无故乱叫
and you know Roy doesn't bark at nothing.
我希望你亲自去看看
I want you to see for yourself.
你必须来看看 求你了
You must. Please.
在狗叫声吵醒我之后
And then after the barking woke me
我听到了别的声音 从那下面传来的
I heard another sound from just below here.
从那下面?
From below?
这 还有那 看到了么
There and there, do you see?
常春藤被拉开了
The ivy's pulled away.
我肯定是吓晕了
I must have fainted.
醒来时天已经亮了
The next thing I knew it was dawn.
你能肯定你不是在做梦 Edith?
You're quite, quite certain you didn't dream this, Edith?
我肯定
Quite.
Jack 我要你全心全意地相信我
Jack, I insist you believe me.
好吧
Very well.
我要你去把这些事告诉福尔摩斯
And that you inform Sherlock Holmes of the facts.
噢 亲爱的
Oh, darling.
不然我就要重新考虑我们的婚事
Or I shall reconsider our engagement.
为什么
But why?
我不能和一个不相信我的人 携手共度此生
I could not give my hand to a man who doubts my word.
华生 如方便请前来
Watson, come at once if convenient.
不方便亦来
If inconvenient come all the same.
福尔摩斯 我收到了你的便条
Holmes, I got your note
是不方便
and it is inconvenient,
确实不方便
damned inconvenient.
你的旧伤又在困扰你了
Your old wound is troubling you.
没有的事
No.
我看未必
I prefer to differ.
你上楼时脚步不稳
Your step was uneven on the stairs.
我做了一天的手术 福尔摩斯
I have a full surgery Holmes.
你得原谅  我有点走神
You must excuse a certain abstraction of mind, Watson.
我知道
I see.
这件事很复杂
It's a tangled scheme.
我正努力找出头绪
I've been looking for the loose end which might unravel it.
以便解决它
One such might reside in the question,
问题的关键在于到底Presbury教授的女儿 是清醒的还是在做梦
does Professor Presbury's daughter wake or dream.
你把我叫来 就为这么个事儿?
I'm summoned here for no more than this?
你肯定听说过Presbury?
You've heard of Presbury?
当然 谁没听说过呢?
Of course, who hasn't?
我们最著名的自然科学家
He's our most distinguished natural scientist.
他是个鳏夫 有一个女儿
He's a widower with one daughter.
他女儿坚持说 夜里有人在她窗边出现
She insists someone appeared at her window last night.
Presbury小姐的卧室在三楼
Ms. Presbury's bedroom is on the second floor
即使是最敏捷的飞贼也没法爬上去
and is completely inaccessible to even the most agile cat burglar.
读一读这个
Read this.
是一点钟的邮车送来的
It arrived by the 1:00 post.
写信的人已经提前来了
The author already arrives ahead of his time,
真是个非常性急的年轻人
a most precipitant young man.
Bennett先生 这是我的朋友和同事华生
Mr. Bennett, my friend and colleague Dr. Watson.
您好
How do you do?
Bennett先生
Mr. Bennett.
请坐
Please sit down.
不 请原谅
No, forgive me.
福尔摩斯先生 恐怕我的判断严重有误
Mr. Holmes, I fear I've made a grave error of judgment.
我本来是不该来找您的
I should not have been in touch with you at all.
我是在浪费你的时间
I've wasted your time entirely.
没有什么合理的理由 能解释Presbury小姐的恐惧
It is not a rational reason for Ms. Presbury's fears.
是的 是无法解释
No, no I can't say that.
这事很微妙
Well it's, it's a delicate matter but I,
我必须请求您不要再继续了
I must beg you to proceed no further.
当然 我会补偿你的
I can of course recompense you.
Bennett先生 你在信里有所隐瞒
Mr. Bennett, your letter was less than frank,
是不是?
was it not?
我说出了全部事实
I set out the facts.
我怀疑不是全部
Not all I suspect.
或许是出于对未婚妻Presbury小姐的忠诚?
Probably out of loyalty to your fiance, Ms. Presbury?
您听说过她?
You're aware of her?
当然 我还听说 你的雇主跟Alice Morphy小姐订了婚
As I am of your employer's engagement to Ms. Alice Morphy,
她可是著名解剖学家的女儿啊
the daughter of the famous comparative anatomist.
她与Presburys家是邻居 是么?
She resides next door to the Presburys, does she not?
你怎么知道他们订婚了?
How do you know of the engagement?
婚讯就登在泰晤士报上 分别是七月一日和九月五日
The Times, July the 1st, September the 5th respectively.
福尔摩斯先生可以说是过目不忘
Mr. Holmes' memory is of a photographical order.
确实是这样
Quite so.
哦 天哪
Oh, dear.
Bennett 我了解你的窘境
Mr. Bennett, I do appreciate your predicament.
作为一个科学家 一个理性主义者
As a scientist and a rationalist yourself
你不愿意采纳
I dare say you're reluctant to accept the evidence
Presbury小姐所坚持的证据
insisted upon by Ms. Presbury.
况且 作为她父亲信任的助手
Further, as a father's trusted assistant
向我求助也陷你于不忠
to have recourse to me must smack to you of disloyalty.
一点不错
Exactly.
我是这个家庭的一份子
I'm part of the family except that Edith,
除非Presbury小姐因为不安而...
Ms. Presbury, she was so upset that she,
Bennett先生 你更愿意疏远谁呢
Mr. Bennett, who would you prefer to alienate,
你未来的妻子还是她那著名的父亲?
your perspective wife or her celebrated father?
你让我陷入两难 都不是
You give me a choice of evils, neither.
那就多告诉我一些事实
Then furnish me with the facts
看我能不能帮助你
and I will see how I can help you.
你可以依赖我们两个的判断力
You may rely on the discretion of both of us.
好吧
Well.
比如说 你会不会把Presbury小姐
Would you for example describe Ms. Presbury,
描述成一个敏感爱幻想的女孩?
as an impressionable, fanciful girl?
不 恰恰相反
No, quite the reverse.
那么Alice Morphy小姐呢
Ms. Alice Morphy?
或许Presbury教授和她订婚
Perhaps Professor Presbury's engagement to her
让你感到意外
came to you as something of a surprise.
毕竟他的年龄是她的三倍
He is after all three times her age.
选这件天鹅绒的?
And this velour?
我更中意
I prefer that one,
带白色羽毛的那一件
with the osprey feathers.
你能去问问他么
Could you ask him, do you think?
我父亲对他的兰花最自豪了
Father's extremely proud of his orchids.
我讨厌它们
I hate them.
它们是那么的
They're so,
怎么说呢 那么的不纯洁
oh I don't know, so impure somehow.
你去跟他说别再送兰花了 好么
Do please ask him not to send them anymore.
我就你这么一个好朋友了 求求你
There's a sweet friend, Edith, please?
-你自己不能去说么 -不
-Can you not ask him? -I couldn't.
我不敢 我很懦弱的
I dare not. I'm such a coward.
-恩 -求求你了
-Well. -Oh, please?
你比我要有个性的多
You've got so much more character than me.
跟他一样有很强的个性
You're as strong as he.
可是Alice
But Alice,
如果你连这个都不敢对我父亲说
if you dare not ask this of my father
那结婚以后 你怎么去处理那些
how will you ever manage those deeper conflicts
即使是最幸福的婚姻中也会存在的冲突呢
that occur even in the happiest of marriages?
我不知道
Oh, I don't know.
我很害怕
I'm so frightened.
害怕和我父亲结婚?
Of marrying my father?
我想是的
I wish,
请别再问了
no, please don't ask.
我们别再谈这个了
Let's not speak of it.
你觉得这个怎么样?
What do you think of this one?
不论是Presbury小姐还是我 都认为她父亲对Morphy小姐的迷恋
Neither Ms. Presbury nor I consider her father's infatuation with Ms. Morphy to be
总的说来不是很合适
... entirely appropriate.
有点极端
Rather excessive.
她的父母 对这门亲事也没有反对吗?
And her parents have no objections to the marriage?
教授是个受人尊敬的鳏夫
The professor is a respectable widower.
而且还很富有
And a wealthy man.
我什么时候能去拜访?
When may I call?
拜访?
Call?
去查看Presbury小姐的窗口
To view Ms. Presbury's window,
亲自去判断
to determine for myself its accessibility
是否存在有人闯入的可能
and otherwise to an intruder.
明天早上11点可以么?
Shall we say 11:00 tomorrow morning?
教授那时会在学校里
Professor Presbury will be at his college.
那就没有问题了
That's of no matter.
我的请求完全合理
At present my inquiries are purely logistical.
我对教授从没有什么隐瞒的
I have never had any secrets from the professor.
Bennett先生
Mr. Bennett,
让我提醒你
let me refer you to your first question,
你事实上已经回答了我的第一个问题
which you have in fact answered.
比起你的雇主
You're more inclined to Ms. Presbury's party
你更倾向于Presbury小姐一方
than you are to your employer's.
是的 我想是这样
Yes, yes, I dare say.
谢谢
Thank you.
再见
Good day.
福尔摩斯 你这是在刺探 一个受人尊敬的家庭的家务事
Holmes, you're prying into the affairs of a perfectly respectable family.
为什么Bennett这么不情愿说出实情?
Why is Bennett so reluctant to tell the truth?
忠诚
Loyalty.
这是显而易见的
It is as plain as a pack staff.
但愿如此
Let us hope so.
但他却是被迫写信给我的
Yet he wrote to me under duress.
你注意到他的笔迹了么
You notice his handwriting,
字母T下笔很重
the crossing of the T's with such deep indentation?
还有他刚来的时候 努力要取消这件事
And then upon his arrival his endeavors to call the whole thing off,
不 这件事可不是看上去的这么简单
no, there's more to this than meets the eye.
我不同意
I do not agree.
杀鸡焉用宰牛刀
This case is unworthy of you.
我得回诊所去了
I must return to my surgery.
或许明天再见喽
Maybe I'll see you tomorrow.
父亲
Father?
亲爱的
My dear.
我想你昨晚睡得好点了吧?
I trust you slept better?
哦 是的
Oh, yes.
昨晚我搬到客房去睡了
Last night I moved to the guest bedroom.
没这个必要
Oh, no need surely.
那只是场噩梦
It was but an ugly dream.
父亲 Alice要我...
Father, Alice has asked me,
什么?
Yes?
实际上她根本不喜欢兰花
The truth is she does not care for orchids.
她不喜欢?
She doesn't?
那她为什么不说呢
Well, why did she not say so?
她不敢说
Well, she was afraid to.
您不知道您是多么令人畏惧
You forget how formidable you are father.
傻女孩
The silly girl.
那她会收到玫瑰的
Well, then she shall have roses.
两打红玫瑰
Yes, two dozen red roses.
Roy昨晚很安静
Roy was quiet enough last night.
别激怒它 先生
Not to rouse him, sir.
它本来很温顺的
Docility itself, (unintelligible).
好吧
All right,
它会适应这些锁链的
He's grown accustomed to his shackles.
可怜的家伙
The poor beast.
我们可以上去么
Shall we go up?
如果Presbury小姐不反对的话
If Ms. Presbury has no objection.
我明白必须这么做
I understand the necessity.
我们来带路吧 亲爱的
Let us lead the way my dear.
我很高兴你今天恢复正常了 华生
I'm glad you're more yourself today, Watson.
你昨天简直像是头熊
You were a veritable bear yesterday.
或许有点脾气不好
A touch liverish perhaps.
就是这出现了人影?
This is where the figure appeared?
是的
Yes.
没有什么梯子
There's no ladder on the premises
能伸到这个高度吧
that could reach this height?
没有
No.
窗子是半开着的?
Was the window ajar?
是的 我把门锁了
Yes, I keep the door locked.
他的手碰到窗玻璃了么?
Did the hand touch the windowpane?
我不知道
I don't know.
我晕过去了
I fainted.
你当然会的 当然
Of course you did, of course you did.
这是令人生畏的高度
Well, that's a formidable elevation,
尽管常春藤很牢固
yet the ivy's strong, Hedera Helixis,
但在那还是给扯断了
torn away just here.
Presbury小姐 你父亲提前回来了
Ms. Presbury, your father has returned prematurely.
哦 不
Oh, no.
不能让他知道你在这里 福尔摩斯先生
He mustn't know you're here Mr. Holmes.
这没法避免
That can scarcely be avoided.
不管怎么说 我们先下去吧
However, let us go down.
从后楼梯?
The backstairs?
当然不是
Certainly not.
Bennett 你是怎么准备我的讲座的?
Bennett, what did you do with my lecture?
你到底是谁 先生?
Who the devil are you, sir?
父亲 对不起
Father, I'm sorry.
这是歇洛克・福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
谁?
Who?
著名侦探
The detective.
Presbury教授
Professor Presbury,
我的名片
my card.
221 B
221 B,
这么个地址很难激起别人的信任
hardly an address to inspire confidence.
我从没想过要激起别人的信任
I have never sought to inspire confidence in others.
我对自己倒是信心十足
I have quite enough of my own.
我来介绍我的同事 华生医生
May I introduce my colleague Dr. Watson?
不必了 你们俩都可以马上离开
Certainly not, you may leave at once the pair of you.
父亲 他们是我们请来的客人
Father, they are here at our request.
我可没有请他们 Edith
But not mine, Edith.
至于你 Bennett
And you Bennett,
在你寻求用这种解决方式前应该和我商量
you should have consulted me before resorting to such methods,
一个平庸的侦探和他的同伙
a common detective and his accomplice, really.
现在 先生们
Now, sir,
我来护送你们从这里出去
allow me to escort you from the premises.
我的助手没有权力雇佣你处理这件事
My assistant had no authority to engage you in this matter.
别再调查它了
Kindly inquire into it no further.
不然的话我会
Should you persist I shall have no hesitation
毫不犹豫的叫警察的
in calling the police.
我和苏格兰场的Lestrade可很熟 所以你最好小心点
Lestrade of Yard is well known to me so beware.
去找Lestrade嘛 我可是会犹疑的 教授
I would hesitate in calling Lestrade, professor,
如果你希望解开这个谜的话
if you wish to have the mystery solved.
压根就没有什么谜 先生 没有
There is no mystery, sir, none.
现在你们可以走了
Now be gone with you
否则我就要放狗了
or would you have me release my dog?
它可分不清
Believe me he'll not distinguish
谁是雇来的私家侦探 谁是入侵者
between a hired snoop and an intruder.
你们还不走吗 先生们?
Will you be gone, sir, will you?
我们会走的 你也别太过分了
We shall, sir, we shall but you are over the mark.
说话要小心点
Kindly watch your words.
这个品种的狗
As a breed,
虽然外表很凶猛
despite their ferocious appearance
实际上举止却并不凶猛
these dogs are seldom vicious.
我很奇怪Roy为什么要整天拴着
I'm surprised that Roy needs chaining at all
除非是为了你的安全吧
unless it is for your safety as much as ours.
华生 狗能反映一个家庭的生活
The dog reflects family life Watson.
真的么
Does it indeed.
谁听说过在阴郁的家庭里有只欢闹的狗
Whoever heard of a frisky dog in a gloomy home
或是在欢乐的家里有只悲伤的狗?
or a sad dog in a happy one?
易怒的人养着易怒的狗
Snarling people have snarling dogs.
你像我一样注意到了 Presbury家的爱尔兰猎狗
You observed the Presbury's Irish wolfhound as well as I.
它对它的主人咆哮着
He growled quite as much at his master as it did at us,
就像对待我们两个陌生人一样
two complete strangers.
这动物毫不掩饰它对教授的敌意
That animal did not reserve its animosity solely for the professor.
等一会Bennett来了 我们会从他那确认这一点的
We'll seek verification from young Bennett when he arrives.
我们在"山羊罗盘"酒馆会面后
I sent word by way of Jack Macphail
我顺道给Jack Macphail捎了信
after our meeting at the Goat and Compasses.
你的另一个密探么 福尔摩斯?
Another of your agents Holmes?
是Presbury家的马车夫
The Presburys' coachman.
他负责看管Roy
He has charge of Roy.
我昨晚跟他一起去找了个小小的乐子
I joined him last night for what he calls a wee Goldie.
Bennett来了 还是那么风风火火
Here's Bennett, precipitous as ever.
请进
Come in.
早上好
Good morning.
福尔摩斯先生 华生医生
Mr. Holmes, Dr. Watson,
我必须为昨天的会面道歉
I must apologize for your unfortunate encounter yesterday.
-但同时... -没必要
-But also... -There's no need.
事实上 恰好给这件怪事
In fact, it has provided the very first clue
提供了第一个线索
to this odd affair.
请坐
Do sit down.
谢谢
Thank you.
福尔摩斯先生 我不能装作
Mr. Holmes, I cannot pretend that I am happy
接到你的邀请时很高兴
to have answered your summons.
当然 我仍然欣赏你
Of course and I continue to appreciate
那分裂的忠诚
the division of your loyalties.
所以你有些事情没有坦诚以告也不足为奇
It's no small wonder that you've withheld so much.
Roy第一次袭击它的主人
Roy first attacked his master on the evening
是在九月二日的晚上 是么?
of September the 2nd, did he not?
你是怎么知道的?
How can you know that?
就在教授从书房去到门厅的时候
As the professor came from his study into the hall
在这种情况下
he restrained the dog.
他拴住狗 把它关在储藏室里
On this occasion he was merely shut up in the scullery.
第二天早晨又一切正常了
The next morning he was as right as rain
这都是Macphail告诉我的
or so Macphail informs me.
Macphail?
还有谁能比家里的马车夫
Who better than the family coachman
更能告诉我实情呢?
to advise me how matters might truly stand?
请原谅 福尔摩斯先生 我应该亲自告诉你这些 但是...
Forgive me Mr. Holmes, I should have told you myself but...
但是你没有
But you didn't.
第二次袭击是在13天后
The second attack occurred 13 days later.
同样 教授是在门厅里
Again, the professor was in the hall.
幸运的是 这一次他关上了书房的门
Fortunately this time he was able to put the study door between himself
挡住了狗 是不是这样?
and the altered animal, was he not?
就是从那会起 Edith希望把Roy锁起来
Edith wanted Roy chained from that moment.
但她父亲不同意
But her father overruled her.
他坚持说它还是条可爱温柔的狗
He insisted that he was still a dear affectionate dog,
本性上不会伤人
that he wasn't congenitally vicious.
那在第三次袭击后呢?
But not after the third attack?
不 他再没有这么说 而是把狗栓了起来
No, he did agree then that he had to be restrained.
然后Roy就被这么被锁在马房里了?
And Roy was banished to the chain in the stable yard.
是的
Yes.
Macphail认为Roy行为的变化
Macphail believes that the change in Roy's behavior
大约是两个月前出现的
stems from about two months ago?
我想或许是的
I think it may have.
我没有特别注意
I, I didn't keep a straight note of it.
去问问你的未婚妻 还有Macphail
Consult your fiance Bennett and Macphail.
关于这件事 有必要做一个
A precise log of these events
确切的记录
may yet prove pertinent.
我注意到教授今天下午
I observed that the professor lectures
两点钟在大学里有个讲座
at the university at 2:00 this afternoon.
到时我会到家里去
I shall call then.
不 我不同意
No, I couldn't possibly agree, no.
Bennett  Presbury小姐不是在做梦
Bennett, Ms. Presbury did not dream.
是有什么人或什么东西探访了她
Someone or something looked in upon her.
我相信你的未婚妻处境极为危险
It is my conviction that your fiance is in grave danger.
来自谁?
From who?
不 先生 应该说是来自什么东西
No, sir, from whom or from what.
作为秘书 你负责处理教授的通信
As secretary you handle the professor's correspondence.
是的 我的职责是是拆阅每一封信
Oh yes, it's my responsibility to open every letter.
Presbury小姐一直习惯于
Has it always been Ms. Presbury's habit
每天晚上锁上卧室的门么
to lock her bedroom door at night?
呃 不
Um, no, well it,
她告诉我...
well she told me that...
什么?
Yes?
那是在Roy举止怪异之后
It was after Roy began to behave so strangely.
她也开始害怕狗了么
That she too became afraid of the dog?
福尔摩斯先生 你不能碰他的书桌
Mr. Holmes, you mustn't touch his desk.
Bennett!
谢谢
Thank you.
告诉我教授和这个叫
Inform me of the correspondence
Dorak的通信情况
the professor had with someone called Dorak
住在Com Read
inhabiting Com Read.
不
No, no, no,
商业街 当然(头字母为CC)
Commercial Road of course CC.
似乎教授本人
It would appear that the professor answers
亲自回复此人的信件
such correspondence himself.
嗯 又是...
Well, again...
又是吞吞吐吐的了
Again, you've been reluctant to speak.
是的
Yes.
大约8周前 他告诉我
Some eight weeks ago he told me that
有一些邮件从东区寄来
certain missives might arrive from East Central
邮票上划着十字
marked by a cross under the stamp.
一个密码?
A code?
这些信是定期寄来的么?
And did they regularly?
不是定期的
Irregularly.
我不得拆阅 也不能跟别人说起
I was to leave them unopened and speak of them to no one.
你说邮件
You said missive.
不光是信么
They were not letters.
有些是 还有些是小包裹
Well, some were, others were small packets.
你注意到 Presbury教授如何回复么?
And did you observe Professor Presbury's replies?
不知道
No.
这些都不由我经手
They didn't pass through my hands.
但有证据表明他确实回信了
Yet the evidence would suggest that he did respond.
印度人认为 狗是猴子的天敌
To the Hindu the dog is a traditional enemy of the monkey.
这说明什么 华生?
What was that Watson?
什么?
What?
没什么
Nothing.
Jack?
哦 我不知道...
Oh, I, I wasn't aware.
我没来得及告诉你 你已经出去了
No, I couldn't tell you, you'd already gone out.
我知道了
I see.
我邀请Alice来和我们喝茶
I've invited Alice to take tea with us.
别对你的未婚夫太严厉了 Presbury小姐
Do not be too severe upon your fiance Ms. Presbury.
他已经尽了全力
He has acted for the best.
另外 也请您继续每晚锁好门
And please will you continue to lock your door at night.
窥视您的可不是普通的生物
The prowler who looked in upon you is no ordinary creature.
再见
Good day.
Jack 你不该带他到这来
Jack, you shouldn't have brought him in here.
我没有 但他坚持要来
I didn't want to but he insisted.
他说这里有极大的危险
He says there's grave danger.
那是歇洛克・福尔摩斯么
Was that Sherlock Holmes?
大侦探福尔摩斯?
The Sherlock Holmes?
你已经观察到了这件事情的核心 华生
Your observation goes to the very heart of this business Watson.
观察?
Observation?
猴子和狗
Considering the monkey and the dog,
-这就是事情的核心 -哦 你这么想?
-the very heart of it. -Oh, you think so?
现在 如果你好心的陪我去大学
Now if you'd be so kind as to accompany me to the university
你还可以继续去商业街
you can drive on to the Commercial Road,
拜访一下Dorak
inquire after Dorak.
商业街可不是个具体地址 福尔摩斯
That's not an address Holmes.
这街有一里多长呢 从东边的Allgate一直到LimeHouse
The Commercial Road is a mile long from Allgate east to LimeHouse.
问问小商贩 Dorak的铺子在哪
We'll ask a custom monger where Dorak's shop.
铺子?
Shop?
走吧 华生 我要迟到了
Come on Watson, I'm going to be late.
在非洲 亚洲和南美洲的
The equatorial rain forests of Africa,
热带雨林中
Asia and Southern America
充满了常见物种的各种声音和活动
are filled with the sound and movement of a multitude of species
以灵长目动物家族为例
from the primate family,
这种身体活动
This physical activity,
像在树枝上晃荡
the swinging amongst branches,
或从一棵树的树顶 跳到另一棵树的树顶
the flying leaps from treetop to treetop
以及发出刺耳的喊叫
and loud raucous calling,
不仅仅是为了捍卫在森林里的势力范围
not only defines territorial rights in the forest.
比如食物的采集
For example for food gathering,
其中大树和灌木的嫩芽
the tender shoots of tree and shrub
是特别的奖励
are particularly prized,
同时也常常是
but also is frequently among
雄性展示力量的一种仪式
the males a ritual display
或者是为了防止不受欢迎的入侵者
either to ward off unwelcome intruders
或者是向某一只雌性
or to impress a particular female
展现它的性潜能
with a sexual potential of the performer.
谢谢诸位
Thank you, gentlemen.
- 下午好 - 你在找人么
Good afternoon, looking for somebody are ya?
我想这附近好像有个马车行
I believe there's some livery stables here or nearby.
没有 隔壁倒是有个妓院
No, no, we got a Macker's Yard next door,
就这样了
that's all.
哦 没错 你是对的
Oh, right, right you are.
此路不通
It's a dead end.
我看倒是可以过去
Oh, I could see a way through, yes.
你是条子还是怎么的
You're a narc or what?
当然不是
Not at all.
走开
Out.
你说什么
I'm sorry.
我说了 走开
I said out.
你是不肯听我的 是吧
You just can't take it in, can you?
-你说什么? -我说了走开 你就给我乖乖的走开
-I beg your pardon? -I said out and I meant out.
这里闲人免进 伙计
No admittance, mate.
这可是商业场所
These are commercial premises.
你这么说是什么意思
What do you mean by that?
我是说这是家商店
I mean it's a shop.
那今天肯定是很早就打烊了
It must be early closing day.
可真够荒唐的
This is ridiculous.
是么?
Is it?
亲爱的Lestrade 你这样的大人物
My dear Lestrade, I'm astonished that you,
竟来调查这么件小事
a man of your standing
真让我惊讶
should call upon so petty an errand.
Presbury教授对你的调查 表示了最强烈的抗议 福尔摩斯
Professor Presbury objects most strenuously to your investigations Mr. Holmes.
他抱怨说那是缺乏正当理由的骚扰
His complaint is that of unjustified harassment.
是否有正当理由还有待证明
The justification has yet to be proved.
Presbury是否把事实都告诉你了?
Has Presbury informed you of the facts?
当然
Of course.
那你的结论是...
And your conclusions?
这女孩在半梦半醒之间
A girl half asleep,
将一只猫或是鸟误认为是闯入者
mistook a cat or a bird or both for an intruder.
就是这样
That's all.
小事一桩
It's trifle.
就这么简单的解释?
Such a simple explanation,
但是 这说明不了家里的那条狗的行为
however, it begs the question of the family dog, does it not?
是不是?
Does it?
什么狗
What dog?
Presbury没有提及在这件事中 Roy的举止怪异么
Presbury did not mention Roy's part in this affair is strange.
好歹Roy也算半个目击者呢
Clearly a partial witness.
我建议你问问他
I suggest you ask him.
你没有掌握这个复杂的案件的全部事实
You're not in full possession of the facts of this complex case.
就算我相信你说的 这事比看上去复杂 福尔摩斯先生
Trust you to say there's more to it than meets the eye, Mr. Holmes.
没有这种刺激的话 我就不从事这个行当了
I never concern myself in anything without that stimulus.
但要是你一意孤行
If you persist you may find yourself
到头来可能会被提起个人诉讼的 你知道么
at the wrong end of a private prosecution you know.
教授是个很坚决的人
Professor Presbury is a determined man.
那和我倒是颇为相似哦
Then we're fairly matched, are we not?
我早知道你会是这样的
I knew it.
好吧 我要说的都说了
Well, I've said my say.
再见了
Mr. Holmes.
再见
Lestrade.
噢 你能行么?
Right, you can do it?
是的 比在Maidstone干的那一票容易
Yeah, easier than Maidstone,
可怜的老家伙
poor old fellow.
商业街144号
144 Commercial Road.
哦 你找到Dorak了 很好
Oh, you located Dorak, good.
就我目前所知道的 表面上看来
He appears to run a general store as far as I can tell.
他经营着一家杂货店 从熨斗到鱼钩什么都有
Sells everything from flatirons to fishhooks.
能说的详细点么?
Can you be more specific?
这家店生意不怎么好
Well, can't be a very prosperous business.
为什么呢?
Why not?
因为普通人是不让进的
Because the general public are not allowed in.
还发现什么?
Did you discover anything else?
除了在店旁的巷子里 被个野蛮的家伙威胁之外
Apart from being threatened by an unhelpful brute
就没有什么了
in an alley at the side, very little.
显然他就在那工作
He obviously works there because he followed me back
因为他又跟着我回到了杂货店 还威胁我
to the shop and threatened me again.
哦 还有另一个衣着光鲜的家伙
Oh, there was another fellow sharply dressed,
穿着马甲 留着小胡子
a waistcoat with a mustache.
叼着雪茄?
A Cheroot?
是的 叼着雪茄
Yes, yes, he did.
听起来像是Harry Wilcox
Sounds like Harry Wilcox,
通常在Soho广场附近活动 而不是东区
more usually of Soho Square than the East End.
还有什么?
Anything further?
没什么了...除了那气味
Not really except the smell.
那地方有种古怪的气味
There was a very odd smell about the place.
是什么的气味?
Of what?
不好说
Well it's not easy to say.
有点像是什么动物的
It belonged to the animal kingdom.
稻草或是马厩?
Straw or stables?
更像是动物园
More like a zoo.
你还没睡啊
You're still up.
是的 先生 我想整理完这些论据
Yes, sir, I thought I might finish these proofs.
你真是太尽责了 但你该去睡了
Very conscientious of you but no, no, you get to bed.
我还是稍等会吧 先生
I'd rather not, sir.
-我想等... -去睡觉
-I should like... -Get to bed.
快去
Go on with you.
好的 先生 好的
Yes, sir, very well.
晚安 先生
Good night, sir.
晚安
Good night.
亲爱的 快醒醒 是我
Darling wake up, it's me.
Edith?
谁啊?
Who is it?
是我 快开门
It's me, open the door.
怎么回事?
What is it?
我看到了
I saw,
没法形容
I can't describe.
那个闯入者
Oh, the intruder.
我们得叫醒你父亲
We must rouse your father.
Presbury教授
Professor Presbury?
父亲
Father?
先生 先生
Sir, sir?
你们俩个怎么啦?
Both of you, what is it?
Jack觉得他看见了...
Jack thought he saw...
我相信
I fancied I,
我听到有人闯入 先生
I heard an intruder, sir.
是么?
You did?
是的 Roy也是躁动不安
Yes, Roy too was exercised
但我朝外看时 却什么都没有
but when I looked out just now there was nothing
Roy也安静了下来
and he since quieted down.
但你说你看到了...
But you thought you saw...
是的 我想我看到了...
Yes, I thought I saw...
什么?
Yes?
一只动物
An animal.
一只动物?
An animal?
不 可能是因为光线的原因看错了
No, it must have been a trick of the light, sir.
一定是这样 先生
Must have been, yes, sir.
是我弄错了
I was mistaken.
很抱歉
My apologies.
晚安
Good night.
Bennett
Bennett?
是的 先生
Yes, sir?
好好睡会
Get some sleep.
会有用的
There's a good chap.
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
"猴子失窃案"
*MONKEY THEFTS"
原来如此
Of course.
华生
Watson?
是同一伙人干的
Unofficially a gang is at work.
其他动物园报告类似的失窃了么?
Other zoological gardens have reported similar thefts?
是的 我在Driscoll的同事在调查
Oh, yeah, my colleagues in Driscoll are investigating the theft
上周两只恒河猴和一只狒狒
of two rhesus monkeys and a baboon
失窃的事
removed only last week.
牛津郡一个马戏团
A traveling menagerie in Oxfordshire
丢了一只珍贵的黑猩猩
lost a prized chimpanzee
还有Maidstone也丢了他们最好的大猩猩
and Maidstone, their finest gorilla.
-"大Charlie"? -是的
-Big Charlie? -Yeah.
那个讨人喜欢的家伙 我很熟悉它
Delightful chap. I knew him well.
它们都消失的无影无踪
Well, they've all disappeared without a trace.
福尔摩斯先生感兴趣的是什么?
And Mr. Holmes, what's his interest?
他认为这可能与他手里的
He insisted to me that this may have relevance
另外一个案子有关
to another case he has in hand.
要是可能的话 一般我们都会迁就他
We like to indulge him when we can.
找到你想要的了么  福尔摩斯先生?
Find anything to the purpose, Mr. Holmes?
没什么
Nothing much.
我告诉过你的
I warned you,
我的人已经把这里仔细梳理过了
my men have been through it with a tooth comb.
开锁的是Stepping Green的Jenkins
The lock was released by Jenkins of Stepping Green.
猩猩是被一小包氯仿给麻醉的
The primate was quieted with a pad of chloroform
这个人头发还上了发蜡
administered by someone who lavishes their hair
是从Jernin街的Brewster先生那买来的
with Mr. Brewster of Jernin Street's Pomade.
这还表明这个人的胡子也上了蜡
This would suggest that he also sports a waxed mustache,
Brewster先生以经营男士发蜡而出名
Mr. Brewster being celebrated for his cosmetic wax for gentlemen.
这么看来 Lestrade
If this was so Lestrade you could do worse
去跟Soho广场的Harry谈谈 是没有坏处的
than have a word with Harry the Tash Wilcox  of Soho.
天啊 福尔摩斯
Good lord Holmes,
对你来说是"没什么" 对别人来说可是了不得的资料了
you're nothing much.Would be anyone else a great deal.
是的 不过我相信 要是我们的人把报告交上来
Yes, well I'm sure my men will arrive at the same conclusion
里头也会有相同的结论的
once their reports are in hand.
你自然也注意到了 Lestrade
You will also naturally have noticed Lestrade
这是这几周来
that this is the sixth reported theft
第六宗成年雄性灵长类动物失窃案了
of a mature male primate in as many weeks.
是嘛 有六起啊?
Is it six?
怪事
Exceptional.
我想重要的是这些失窃动物的性别
The gender of the animals removed is I suggest of the essence.
再见
Good day.
请进
Come in.
我最亲爱的Alice
My dearest Alice.
我没有打扰你的工作吧?
I'm not interrupting your work?
没有
No, no.
我也没有忙什么
I wasn't seriously engaged,
只是整理些笔记以备查考 没什么的
just some notes of future inquiry, nothing more.
我们去客厅好么
Shall we go to the drawing room?
年轻女士在这儿恐怕不会感到愉快
This is hardly the place to entertain a young lady.
不必了
No.
哦 天哪
Oh, dear.
我亲爱的 怎么了?
My dear child, what is the matter?
我以前就该告诉你的
I ought to have said before.
告诉什么?
Ought to what?
你得把这个收回去
There, you must take it back.
可是 Alice
But Alice.
我不能嫁给你
I can't marry you.
我以前不该答应的
I shouldn't have said I would,
但我不敢说不
but I was afraid to say no.
请你拿回去
Please take it back.
-胡说 这只不过是... -不 你得拿回去
-Nonsense, This is simply... -No, you must take it.
很对不起
There, I'm sorry.
Alice
Alice.
不 你很老
No, you're old,
太老了
you're too old.
这么说 Bennett确实在房子里看到了 闯入者的影子
So, Bennett actually saw the intruders shadow inside the house.
但却查不出任何的蛛丝马迹
But upon investigation could find no further trace.
你得让屠夫家的男孩把这个交给他
You must get this to him by way of the butcher's boy.
你要来么?
Are you coming?
去哪?
Where to?
去Dorak的杂货铺
Dorak's Emporium,
特别是Jenkins守着 不让你进去的那些地方
especially those parts where Jenkins took such pains to guard against you.
-有兴趣么? -很乐意去
-Are you game? -Delighted.
你带着武器去?
You go armed?
我去Allgate东区从来都带着枪的 华生
Always carry a firearm east of Allgate, Watson.
我担心的就是这个
It's as I feared.
我们就等着你来访呢 福尔摩斯先生
We was waiting on a visit, Mr. Holmes.
Wilcox
Wilcox!
还有Jenkins
And Jenkins.
老天作证 福尔摩斯
By heavens Holmes,
我闻到的就是这个味道
this is what I smelt.
这就是Dorak的病人
These are Dorak's patients,
被虐待的可怜家伙
poor abused creatures.
你看过Dorak
Have you observed the experiments
在它们身上做手术么?
that Dorak performs on them?
没有 他说这不关我们什么事
Oh, no that's none of our business he says.
那就算你自己走运
Well count yourself fortunate
不会起诉到你的
that the process has been kept from you.
现在 先生们 进去吧
Now gentlemen in you go.
到里面去 跟它在一起? 为什么?
In there with him? Why?
等着警察来
To await the police.
进去 先生们
In gentlemen.
我会让Lestrade探长马上过来
I should advise Inspector Lestrade at once.
你不能把我们关在这
You can't leave us in here.
别忘了大猩猩也是爱交际的动物
Remember the gorilla is a social animal
如果你俩都注意举止
and if you both mind your manners
我敢说你们会相处的很融洽的
you will do well enough I dare say.
Bennett先生 还有Presbury小姐
Mr. Bennett and Ms. Presbury.
是的
Yes.
我决定要陪着Jack 福尔摩斯先生
I decided I had to accompany Jack, Mr. Holmes.
我很高兴
I'm delighted.
有没有把举止失常的日期列出来?
Have you brought the list of missing dates?
是的 还有Roy在这些日子里也都叫了
Yes, Roy also barked on these nights.
先别管那个了 福尔摩斯先生
Please never mind that Mr. Holmes.
我们还有更紧急的事要告诉您
We have far more urgent matters to impart.
是什么?
Is that so?
Morphy小姐解除了和我父亲的婚约
Ms. Morphy has renounced my father.
她把戒指也退回来了?
She's returned his ring?
是的 就在今天
Today.
然后教授就把自己反锁在书房
Since when he has remained locked in his study.
每次我去敲门他都粗暴地向我喊叫
Every time I've knocked he's shouted abuse at me.
我们担心...
We, we fear...
这些数字之间有什么联系 华生
The logic of it Watson,
你看出来了么?
of this progression, do you see it?
是什么?
Please?
最开始的三次是显而易见的
The first three occasions are self-evident.
我们都知道
We know of those.
在10月5日发生了什么?
What happened on the 5th of October?
Roy整个晚上都在叫 12日也是
Roy barked all night, on the 12th too.
这也是教授收到从伦敦东区
They're also days upon which the professor
寄来的包裹的日子
received packages from London East Central.
这天是在窗口出现了人影的时间
This is the date on which the face appeared
在四天前?
at the window four nights ago?
是的
Yes.
这是昨晚你看到黑影的时间
And this is where the shadow appeared last night.
对了
Of course!
共同的因素有两个
The common factor is two.
总是有两天的间隔
Always the gap decreases by two days.
我真是个傻瓜
Numskull, Holmes.
而今天是10月21日
And today is the 21st of October.
有么?
Did?
是的 有个包裹 今天早上到的
Yes, a package arrived this morning.
决定性的时刻到了
And the crisis is upon us.
昨晚不过是个序幕
Last night was but the precursor.
快 我们得马上出发
Come, we must go at once.
快 快点 路上再给你们解释
Come along, come along, I'll explain on the way.
前门是开的
The front door is open.
Bennett 到楼上检查
Bennett, examine upstairs.
华生
Watson.
果然如此
I thought as much.
你听见了么 福尔摩斯先生?
Did you hear Mr. Holmes?
听到了 Prsbury小姐 听的很清楚
Too well, Ms. Presbury, too well.
看那上面 快看
Up there, look.
老天啊 福尔摩斯 你说对了
My heavens Holmes, you were right.
他朝Morphy小姐家走了
He's headed across to Ms. Morphy's house.
Bennett 留在这保护小姐
Bennett stay here and protect Ms. Presbury.
他的目标是阳台
He's aiming for that balcony.
门是锁上的
It's locked.
狗 华生 留心狗
The dog Watson, the dog.
走开
Stay away,
请你走开
please keep away.
真是侥幸
It was a close thing,
差一点就咬到颈动脉了
just missed the carotid artery.
他还好么?
Is he all right?
性命没有大碍
He'll live.
我相信这件事之后 他会改过自新
A reformed man I have no doubt after his experience.
亲爱的Lestrade 我希望把这事归功于你
My dear Lestrade I quite intended you to have the credit
但要指证Dorak Wilcox和Jenkins 了结这案子
but to complete the case against Dorak, Wilcox and Jenkins
你还需要这个
you'll need this.
这是确实的证据
Here is the incontrovertible proof
他们偷那些动物
that those animals you've rescued from degradation
为的就是获取血清
were stolen for the sake of their glands.
那些动物被高价买卖
The animal extract was sold at an enormous profit
是因为有些十分愚蠢或绝望的人
to those foolish or desperate enough
幻想用它们的血清
to imagine that a course of serum
来恢复青春
could restore their lost vitality
而没有其他副作用
without any other effects.
我十分感激你 福尔摩斯先生
I am grateful to you Mr. Holmes.
因为有你 我们才查到了犯罪的源头
Thanks to you we've traced the evil to its source.
也许吧 可是可怜的Presbury
Perhaps, but poor Presbury.
一个人想要凌驾于自然
When one tries to rise above nature,
他就会堕落到丧失本性
one is liable to fall below it.
最高等的人
The highest type of man
一旦偏离了人类注定的轨迹
may revert to the animal
就会变成动物
when he leaves the straight road of destiny.
哲学上的事情还是留给你自己去想吧 福尔摩斯先生
Yes, well I'll leave the philosophy to you Mr. Holmes.
真是明智之举 Lestrade 我一向都是这么干的
Quite the best Lestrade, I always do.
那条爱尔兰猎狗要人道毁灭么?
Is the wolfhound to be destroyed?
不 不 Roy攻击的是猴子 而不是人
Oh, no, no it was the monkey that Roy attacked, not the man.
狗会和他的主人一样都恢复原样的
But the dog will be himself again quite as much as his master.
谢谢二位
Well, thank you both.
再见 先生们
Good day, gentlemen.
再见 Lestrade
Good day Lestrade.
如果我可以这么说的话 福尔摩斯
If I my say so Holmes
我觉得你给予Lestrade过多的功劳了
I think you went a little too far in allowing Lestrade all the credit.
不全是这样 华生
Not all Watson.
你可以把它存在我们的办案记录里
You can file it away in our archives.
总有为人所知的那一天的
One day the entire truth can be told.